{
  "reference_number": "11792",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "I strongly support the immediate creation of a Zero Carbon Act. We have been doodling and noodling around for far too long.\n Companies, the market and consecutive governments have failed people and the planet. While I don't think that the creators of our\n climate crisis - governments and businesses - will solve this problem, I support any moves made that help towards immediate\n\n reduction in emissions."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "The most ambitious target: reducing total greenhouse gases! I further think that this should not happen by 2050, but a lot sooner.\n Let's 2040. But ideally even sooner. I also support taking a science-based approach to ensure our efforts to reduce emissions are as\n\n impactful as possible: we should aim for negative levels of long-lived gases, while reducing short-lived gases to sustainable levels."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "Immediate halt to the industrial dairy madness that is destroying the lives of farmers and cows. Rivers are suffering and the climate is\n being destroyed. We need an immediate shift to a regenerative farming model, away from the exponential decay that is the Fonterra\n way of producing milk solids for export. Unused land can be returned back to native forest as carbon sinks."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Only to lower the target (say to 2030)."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "But long-term planning needs more than thinking ahead 15 years. We need to think several generations ahead to avoid another\n human-created mess."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "No - emissions budgets should not be able to be changed",
      "answer_index": 9,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I agree that the Government and the Climate Commission should take the following factors into consideration when advising on and\n\nsetting budgets: • scientific knowledge regarding climate change • technology relevant to climate change • economic\ncircumstances and the likely impact of a decision on the economy, as well as the competitiveness of particular sectors of the\n\neconomy • fiscal circumstances and the likely impact of the decision on taxation, public spending and public borrowing • social\ncircumstances and the likely impact of a decision on fuel poverty • energy policy and the likely impact of a decision on energy\nsupplies and the carbon and energy intensity of the economy."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes - we must learn from the mistakes of the UK's Climate Change Act and specify a strict time frame for producing a plan."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "It shouldn’t have decision making powers due to the undemocratic nature of the commission, and to avoid conflicts of interest if it\nends up basically monitoring itself. However, to ensure transparency and accountability, the Government must table all its reports in\n\nParliament."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I think the ETS should be abolished. It's a false solution that only helps the rich and powerful."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I agree with the following collective expertise: • climate change policy (including emissions trading) • resource economics and\nimpacts (including social impacts, labour markets and distribution) • te Tiriti o Waitangi, te reo me ona tikanga Māori and Māori\n\ninterests • climate and environmental science including mātauranga Māori • experience with addressing adaptation challenges like\nplanning, insurance and local government • risk management • engineering and/or infrastructure • community engagement and\n\ncommunications. • business competitiveness • knowledge of the public and private innovation and technology development system.\nI think expertise in public health is also important."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "We are already experiencing the impacts of 1˚C of warming - and we have seen marine heatwaves, causing our hottest summer ever\n\nthis year, along with extreme flooding events and cyclones hitting many parts of the country. Until now, the Government has relied on\nregional councils to come up with their own planning for this, but many of them are calling for national guidance. Climate change is a\n\nreality. For example, where I live, in Taranaki, we are going from drought, to floods, from storms to super-storms. Sea-level rise will\nimpact the Taranaki coast heavily. Erosion in northern Taranaki is already now eating houses and paddocks. This is real!"
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I agree with the proposed functions below, but recognise that nuance is required in terms of how local councils are involved: • a\n\nnational climate change risk assessment • a national adaptation plan • regular review of progress towards implementing the national\nadaptation plan • an adaptation reporting power The Government must produce an Adaptation Programme to address the climate\nrisks identified in the National Climate Risk Assessment."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Climate Justice Now! We need to stop the drilling for fossil fuels in Taranaki. This madness must end. We need to move to a low-\ncarbon economy, away from this dog-eat-dog mentality that is capitalism. Ngā mihi"
    }
  ]
}
